A Guide to the Papers of John Powell, 1888-1978, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series IV: Eugenics and Racial Integrity
  - C. Correspondence concerning Eugenics: Plecker
    - W. A. Plecker to Dr. J. A. Drake, Jr., March 31, 1943, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:27)
      Plecker writes that he received the birth certificate for Douglas McArthur Lawless and he needs Dr. Drake to sign it. He also writes that the racial designation on the certificate must be changed to show the correct race of colored. He writes, "Please bear in mind that we cannot accept certificates for any of the free issue people of Amherst or Rockbridge county as other than colored, mulatto, issue, or negro."
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. Harry W. Tyree, March 31, 1943, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:28)
      Plecker writes that the birth certificates from the Tyree family indicate their race as white but this classification cannot be accepted unless they can prove that the father is a member of a white Tyree family of Amherst or Rockbridge County.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. Lawrence H. Hartless, April 1, 1943, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:29)
      Plecker writes that the father of all three children must sign a form acknowledging that he is the father and it will also be necessary for her to sign a form stating that she previously gave "wrong information." According to the questionnaire that Mrs. Hartless filled out, her mother is Bessie Anderson Dempsey, daughter of the Sorrels.
    - W. A. Plecker to John Powell, April 5, 1943, TM, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:30)
      Note about a news clipping in The News Leader: Two Given Terms in Draft Violation, Everett Hugo Byrd and Russell Collridge Fortune were charged with"failing to report for induction into the armed forces." They were sentenced to two years in a Federal reformatory by Judge Robert N. Pollard.
    - W. A. Plecker to the Honorable John Collier, Commissioner, Office of Indian Affairs, April 6, 1943, TLS, 3 pp. (Box-folder 42:31)
      Plecker defends his actions in preventing Ruth Rogers Garret from trying to pass as Indian. Garret's consort, Jasper Thomas Garrett had complained about Plecker to the Office of Indian Affairs and Plecker's boss, Dr. I. C. Riggin, State Health Commissioner. Plecker invites Colliers staff to come and see the research of Miss Kelly. Plecker writes "Your staff member is probably correct in his surmise that Hitler's genealogical study of the Jews is not more complete."
    - W. A. Plecker to Norman Lawhorne, April 8, 1943, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:32)
      Plecker writes that Mr. Lawhorne's questionnaire is incomplete. Plecker states that without any information about his grandparents, it is impossible to issue him a certificate.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. Nellie Crum, April 9, 1943, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:33)
      Plecker writes that he cannot accept the birth certificate for Nellie Randolph Hicks because both parents are listed as white while records of other family members in the past have shown the racial status as colored.
    - W. A. Plecker to Ivy Lewis April 21, 1943, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:34)
      Plecker responds to a letter of criticism that he receives from a University of Virginia student, L. G. Moffatt, "They, like many others, without knowing the facts, have misjudged us and think that we are harsh on the negroes as a whole. Any harsh feeling is only for the portion of the race trying by various maneuvers to escape into the white race..."
    - W. A. Plecker to L. G. Moffatt April 21, 1943, TLS, 3 pp. (Box-folder 42:35)
      Plecker responds to Moffatt's criticism by explaining that Plecker was referring only to "negroes" that want to pass as white. Plecker describes these families in Amherst County, Virginia as "free issue" people or "rats" trying to "sneak in" and obtain white or Indian birth certificates. He also mentions that his office tries to help the "negroes" who accept their "colored " status because they have more problems than white people and are less able to take care of themselves. Plecker recommends that Moffatt talk about the racial issue with Dr. Ivy Lewis and cites some literature for him to read.
    - W. A. Plecker to the Honorable Herbert G. Smith, Judge of the Corporation Court, Newport News, Virginia April 22, 1943, TLS, 4 pp. (Box-folder 42:36)
      Plecker reveals information from his records stating that William Thomas Edward Price is colored and gives Smith a background on the family lineage. He also explains that the optional registration (as opposed to mandatory) places a great burden on the State Registrar. Plecker defends criticism about his use of power and writes that they try to be "correct as far as is in our power the great evil of racial intermixture..." Plecker also mentions a new law that removes the power from judges to determine race.
    - W. A. Plecker to Miss Eleanor M. Anderson, Clerk, Lynchburg, May 7, 1943, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:37)
      Plecker answers her inquiry about the racial status of Willie Branham by writing that the Branham family is from "negro origin." He advises that she should "classify this boy as colored." He also warns her of the consequences of altering a certificate.
    - Copy of the information written on the back of the birth certificate of Edward Parker Willis by W. A. Plecker, May 7, 1943, TMS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:38)
      Plecker states that Willis is a "free colored" and not Indian.
    - W. A. Plecker to Dr. R. R. Kason, May 8, 1943, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:39)
      Plecker writes that he is returning the certificate for Bonnie Jane Arthurs because Kason gives the race of the father and mother as white and this family belongs to the "free issue" group of Irish Creek. He also reminds Kason that it is a felony to falsely report the racial status.
    - W. A. Plecker to Edwin P. Hamilton, May 25, 1943, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:40)
      Plecker writes that before his office can accept the birth certificate of his child, they need to have more information about his family.
    - W. A. Plecker to Nancy S. Hundley, Superintendent of Public Welfare, Cumberland, Virginia, July 19, 1943, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:41)
      Plecker explains that the birth of an illegitimate child of a white mother and colored father needs to be reported. He also advises that the child be brought into the Bureau of Vital Statistics and examined for racial characteristics. He writes, "Psychological examination or blood tests do not show the race. That has to be decided upon what can be seen and learned."
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. Bruce Clemons, July 20, 1943, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:42)
      Plecker writes that he is sending her a copy the Racial Integrity Act of 1924 which shows that "no white person in Virginia is permitted to intermarry with any of the Asiatic races." He also writes that, "Filipinos are included in the Malay class."
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. Helen Dunges, July 21, 1943, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 42:43)
      Plecker answers her inquiry of the racial status of her recent husband by writing that the Dunge family are "negroes." However, he writes that to absolutely certify that her husband is colored Plecker would need more information about her husband's parents and grandparents. Plecker asks her to fill out a questionnaire. He also writes, "Please tell us what his appearance is. Do negro characteristics show in his hair and features?"
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. Lillie Carroll, July 22, 1943, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:44)
      Plecker writes that he is not accepting her birth certificate as it is filled out, because her mother and father are from the Gibson and Collins' families that are descendants of "melungeons."
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. F. C. Drummond, Chairman, Amherst County Selective Service, July 24, 1943, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:45)
      Plecker responds that the Clarke family has been trying aggressively to pass as white and advises Drummond that as a local resident of Amherst he is in a better position to judge for himself whether these people are colored or not.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. Nancy S. Hundley, Superintendent, Cumberland County Public Welfare Board, July 27, 1943, 1 TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:46)
      Plecker responds to her letter about the "promiscuous sexual habits of Mattie Murray, the feeble-minded white woman who seems to have given birth to one or two mulatto children" by writing that the proper thing to do without loss of time is to "place this woman in the State Colony and have her sterilized." He also advises that the local officials are the best judge of determining the race based on the appearance of the mulattoes.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. Jessie Lee Collins, July 28, 1943, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:47)
      Plecker writes that he cannot accept his birth certificate because he is related to the Collins family who are "members of the group known as Melungeons, who are of mixed negro stock."
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. Taylor Gibson, July 28, 1943, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:48)
      Plecker writes that he cannot accept his birth certificate because his parents are from the Gibson and Collins family who are known as "Melungeons."
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. Ovis Shaw, July 28, 1943, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:49)
      Plecker writes that he needs more information on the Shaw family before he can accept his birth certificate.
    - W. A. Plecker to John Powell, October 13, 1943, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:50)
      Plecker writes that the Attorney General decided that the birth certificates for two of the Branham children can be issued without any comments stating that they are colored. Plecker states, "This is the worst backset which we have received since Judge Holt's decision." Plecker's recourse is that they will ensure that the certificates are accurate before they accept them. Plecker confesses, "I have been doing a good deal of bluffing, knowing all the time that it could not be legally sustained. This is the first time my hand has absolutely been called."
    - W. A. Plecker to Miss Aileen Hartless, March 9, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:51)
      Plecker writes that he is returning her birth certificate with a note on the back which indicates the certificate contains false information pertaining to racial status. Plecker warns her, "I have no doubt at all but that it is all embarrassing for you. Your parents started out to make false statement about themselves, and their children are suffering...After the war it is possible that some of these cases will come into court. We might try this one. It would make a good one, if you continue to try to be what you are not."
    - W. A. Plecker to the Reverend J. J. Murray, March 20, 1944, TLS, 2 pp. on 11. (Box-folder 42:52)
      Plecker is eager to know the race of the illegitimate children of Nellie Lee Clarke because they are living in the orphanage that he is planning on including in his will. Plecker writes that these children with their heredity and poor nurturing would be harmful to the other children in the orphanage.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. Mary Lula Mullins, March 23, 1944, TLS, 1 pp. (Box-folder 42:53)
      Plecker writes that he cannot accept the birth certificate for Mary Lula Collins because she answers the questionnaire with "I don't know."
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. M. L. Williams, April 17, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:54)
      Plecker writes that he received the birth certificates for Kate Johns, Fred Benson Johns, and Aubrey Louis Johns in which the race is falsely designated as Indian. Plecker also writes that due to the passage of a recent law, it his duty is to write on the back of a birth certificate when he believes it contains false information. He explains that this new law places the burden on Plecker's office instead of on the local registrars.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. Sadie M. Bane, Superintendent, Department of Public Welfare, Bland, Virginia, April 24, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:55)
      Plecker writes that he needs the names of the children and their birthplace in order to determine their racial origin. It is his understanding that Elbert Proffit is "a Negroid." Plecker also inquires as to the appearance of the children and whether they show any "negro features and characteristics."
    - . A. Plecker to Clerk of the Hancock County Court, Tennessee, April 24, 1944, 1 TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 42:56)
      Plecker writes that he needs information from their earliest records on the Gibson and Collins family. Plecker is particularly interested in the records for Commodore M. Collins.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. Ernest Franklin Arthurs, April 27, 1944, 1 TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:57)
      Plecker responds to a letter from Mr. Arthurs that he does not know to whom Arthurs is referring but assumes that it is one of Arthurs' children. Plecker explains that the John's family in Amherst County are from "free negro stock." Plecker encourages Arthurs to submit any evidence by filling out the questionnaires.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. William M. Cleveland, April 29, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:58)
      Plecker writes that the wife of Mr. Cleveland "belongs to a group of mixed breeds of Amherst and Rockbridge, known locally as free issues." The certificates for the nephews of Mrs. Cleveland were accepted several years ago as they came in because the office was swamped with inquiries. Plecker advises that the only way that these certificates can now be accepted is to "have the racial pedigree noted on the back of the certificate."
    - W. A. Plecker to Senator Lloyd M. Robinette, May 4, 1944, TLS, 2 p. (Box-folder 42:59)
      Plecker writes that it is difficult to establish the racial origin of Commodore M. Collins due to a lack of records. Plecker believes that Collin's grandfather is Solomon Collins who is listed in Carter G. Woodson's book as a Negro. Therefore he cannot register any of the Collins descendants as white. Plecker states that his wife is definitely white. He writes, "Probably she did not know the sort of family she was marrying into. The fact that he has probably good blood from good white stock to enable him to rise above his early surrounding does not remove the racial condition."
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. H. C. Jefferson, May 9, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:60)
      Plecker writes that she needs to fill out the questionnaire giving more family history. He writes, "Be sure to answer every question correctly and do not say that you 'don't know.' That expression does not establish any facts."
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. Edith Butcher, May 9, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:61)
      Plecker writes that he is holding her birth certificate because of a lack of evidence regarding her racial status. Plecker writes, "We are not willing to take chances when there is no positive evidence. The question is too involved for us to be able to handle at this time. It is not necessary for you to make further effort to register your birth."
    - W. A. Plecker to Miss. Janey B. Reel, May 10, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:62)
      Plecker writes that he received the birth certificates for Oma R. Collins (Williams) and Ronald Earl Williams with the signature of the midwife but he does not understand why the midwife signed the certificates in pencil when the rest of it is signed with ink in Miss Reel's handwriting.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. H. C. Jefferson, May 15, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:63)
      Plecker writes again to Mrs. Jefferson asking her to give his office more information. He writes that if she cannot show when and where she was married, her children "will be considered illegitimate." He also writes that there will be no certified copies for the certificates until these questions are answered.
    - W. A. Plecker to R. E. Moore, Superintendent, Presbyterian Orphans Home, Lynchburg, May 18, 1944, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 42:64)
      Plecker writes that according to the family tree, Nellie Clark and her illegitimate children in the orphanage are "of mixed stock and not white." Plecker writes that illegitimate children of mixed stock are dangerous for other children in the orphanage.
    - W. A. Plecker to Okla Collins, May 26, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:65)
      Plecker writes that he cannot place her birth certificate on file because her records are from Kentucky and North Carolina and his office only traces records from Virginia.
    - W. A. Plecker to Guy Lawrence Hayslett, May 31, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:66)
      Plecker writes that he needs more information on the ancestry of Elizabeth Ann Floyd before he can accept the birth certificate for his daughter Betty Lou Hayslett.
    - W.A. Plecker to Mrs. Oma R. Collins Williams, May 31, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:67)
      Plecker writes that he has received two birth certificates for Oma Collins Williams and her husband Ronald Earl Williams, but he will need more information since they were born prior to 1912.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. James P. Greene, June 1, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:68)
      Plecker writes that he received Greene's birth certificate but the race of his parents is designated as "Indian " and Plecker needs to know when and where his parents were married and whether or not there were any other children.
    - W. A. Plecker to the Selective Service, Lynchburg, Virginia, June 19, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:69)
      Plecker responds to their inquiry on the racial status of Clarence Loving Branham by writing that he is sending them a photocopy of the certificate in which the midwife states that both of Branham's parents are colored. Plecker asks that no one know that the midwife designated the racial status as colored, "as a matter of protection for her."
    - W. A. Plecker to Clayton B. Pugh, July 19, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:70)
      Plecker writes that he is sending Pugh a new certificate with a statement on the back revealing that his mother is "of negro descent." He also writes, "If members of your family have certificates stating that they are white, they had better keep very quiet about them or return them to have them properly corrected. There are plenty of jobs open for colored people. You need have no trouble about that."
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. Oggie Vanover, July 24, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:71)
      Plecker writes that he cannot accept her birth certificate because she did not fill out the information giving the names of her father's grandparents and great grandparents.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. Lucy Hoffman, August 11, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:72)
      Plecker writes that the four birth certificates for her children cannot be accepted because the race of her parents is falsely designated as white. He requests that she write all the names and birthdays of the children on the back of one the certificates. He also writes, "All marriages between a white person and a colored person...shall be absolutely void. You cannot be the wife of a colored man."
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. Solomon Collins, August 12, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:73)
      Plecker writes that he his holding Collins' birth certificate until the "question of your pedigree is established." Plecker points out that Collins has contradicted himself about where his grandfather is born. Plecker also writes that without the records of North Carolina and Tennessee, he cannot trace the ancestry or accept Collins' birth certificate.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. E.P. Hyman, American Red Cross, August 18, 1944, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 42:74)
      Plecker asks the Red Cross if the Turners are trying to pass as Indian. He writes, "Their efforts seem to be looked upon sympathetically by the Bureau of Indian Affairs, which has endeavored to declare large groups as Indian by proclamation." Also J. E Daniel, Chairman of the Selective Service has responded to Plecker that Turner is illegitimate, his racial status is falsely designated as white, and that Turner is a member of a group that calls themselves Portuguese.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. Gillie Ann Cooley, August 18, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:75)
      Plecker writes that he cannot accept the birth certificate for her son, David because of a lack of background information. He writes, "It is too bad that a person of your age, 80 years old, can tell us nothing at all about your grandparents...It is useless to write further unless you can answer the questions which we asked."
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. James A. Lethcoe, August 29, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:76)
      Plecker writes that he cannot accept the birth certificate for her child, Ellamae Pearl Lethcoe because she has given conflicting information on the names of her parents.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. W. R. Harrup, Manager, Western Union Telegraph Company, September 9, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:77)
      Plecker responds that there is no birth certificate on file for Herman Carl Floyd but he can send a form and questionnaire so that he can be registered. He reminds them that registering falsely is a felony and carries a penalty of one year in the penitentiary.
    - W. A. Plecker to Employment Certificating Service, Murrell Dobbins Vocational School, October 13, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:78)
      Plecker writes he has received their request "for a birth certificate for a negro, Gilbert Emerson Page" but the facts are inaccurately given for racial status; Indian instead of "negro."
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. T. Moore Butler, Commonwealth Attorney, Covington, Virginia, October 18, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:79)
      Plecker writes that he is sending him a photostat copy of the birth certificate of Betty Lou Margret Thompson. He also writes that an "Act of 1944 requires his office to put on the backs of the original certificate... information as to the pedigree when incorrect statements as to race have been made."
    - W. A. Plecker to Miss Jean M. Lambeth, October 19, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:80)
      Plecker writes that he needs more information on the birth certificate for Mrs. Daisy Lyons Wingate, daughter of William B. Lyons and Clara Catherine Gibson."Since you have vouched for these people and realize the seriousness of it, we expect you to make a special effort to obtain the truth for us."
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. [Miss] Jean Lambeth, October 23, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:81)
      Plecker writes that she gives no evidence that Clara Catherine Gibson, the mother of Mrs. Daisy Lyons Wingate, is white. He advises her to tell the Gibsons that more information is needed and that if they are white they would want to give the information so it could be placed in their records for their future protection.
    - W. A. Plecker to Dr. A. L. Herring, October 27, 1944, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 42:82)
      Plecker writes that he has received the birth certificate for Elmer Davis Adams and responds that the "Adams and Allmond families belong to stock descended from the free negroes..." He advises that the simplest thing to do is to have a doctor sign a new certificate. He also warns that the Grace Hospital watch carefully when admitting patients. He adds that the University of Virginia Hospital often writes to his office to verify the race of some patients.
    - W. A. Plecker to Miss Katherine E. Taliaferro, Clerk, Selective Service, Isle of Wight, Virginia, November 1, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:83)
      Plecker responds to her inquiry that, according to the certificate on file, the race of the mother, Mary Elizabeth Gay is given as "Mixed."
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. Roger Edwards, November 3, 1944, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 42:84)